Guide to the William Palmer Ladd Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
William Palmer Ladd Papers
1897-1943
RG 136
Yale University Divinity School Library
3
7 boxes
Correspondence, sermons, writings, and collected material document the work of William Palmer Ladd (1870-1941), who was Dean of Berkeley Divinity School from 1918 to 1941. Of particular interest is documentation related to charges of socialism brought against Berkeley Divinity School and its Dean following a lecture on Russia delivered at the school in December 1919.
Ladd, William Palmer, 1870-1941
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of John Ladd, 2015.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
William Palmer Ladd was born in Lancaster, New Hampshire on May 13, 1870. He graduated from Dartmouth College in 1891 and received a B.D. degree from General Theological Seminary in 1897. He also studied abroad at the University of Paris, Oxford University, and the University of Leipzig. Ladd was ordained deacon on June 11, 1897 and as a priest on June 11, 1898. He served St. Barnabas Church in Berlin, New Hampshire from 1897 to 1902. Ladd was professor of history at Berkeley Divinity School from 1904 to 1941 and Dean of the school from 1918 until his death in 1941. It was during his tenure as Dean that Berkeley moved from Middletown, Connecticut to New Haven.
Ladd was noted for his progressive views on economic and justice issues. In 1919-1920 a controversy arose regarding activities at Berkeley and Ladd was labeled at "Bolshevist", leading to an investigation by a special committee. Ladd served on the Connecticut Child Welfare Commission during the same period.
According to an article by Michael Moriarity in Church History (September, 1995), "The liturgical movement in the American Episcopal Church owes its origin to William Palmer Ladd (1870-1941), a pragmatic New England Yankee whose ideas helped reorient the church's worship and self-understanding, and came to fruition in the current liturgy, the 1979 Book of Common Prayer."
Ladd died in New Haven on July 1, 1941.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the academic and professional career of William Palmer Ladd and provides valuable insight on issues in American society, especially during the early 1920s. Correspondence, sermons, and writings document the views of Ladd, a prominent Episcopal educator, on theological and social issues. Documentation related to the "socialist controversy" at Berkeley Divinity School (1919-1920) and the Connecticut Child Welfare Commission (1918-1921) is detailed and substantial.
Additional correspondence, writings, and biographical documentation relating to William Palmer Ladd are contained in the archives of Berkeley Divinity School, Record Group 216.
Series I, Correspondence, contains few personal letters. The bulk of the correspondence relates to the socialist controversy at Berkeley, Ladd's work with the Child Welfare Commission, and comments on Ladd's "Prayer Book Interleaves" - a series of articles that were later published as a book..
The Writings and Notes of Ladd in Series II include many handwritten sermons dating from his ordination in 1897 until his death in 1941. Addresses and talks include Ladd's discourses on the opening of the school year at Berkeley from 1933 to 1937. His published articles and essays are often focused on the interpretation of theology and church history for a lay audience, including a series titled "A Bird's Eye View of Church History."
Series III, Collected Material, contains valuable documentation of the socialist controversy at Berkeley, including many clippings and articles from local and regional newspapers and church organs. Reports, minutes, and articles relating to the work of the Connecticut Child Welfare Commission also provide an interesting snapshot of social conditions in Connecticut in the early 1920s.
Series IV, Personal Items and Memorabilia, includes a photographic portrait of Ladd and an article by the donor, Rosalind Ekman Ladd, relating to New Hampshire history of the Ladd family.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Writings and Notes of Ladd
III. Collected Material
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia
Theology -- Study and teaching -- Episcopal Church; Socialism -- United States; Child welfare -- Connecticut; Ladd, William Palmer, 1870-1941; Berkeley Divinity School; Connecticut. Commission on Child Welfare
- Correspondence, 1900-1942; I
  - Personal and professional correspondence
    - Letters to/from Ladd, including with the Library of Congress and The Churchman journal, 1900-1918 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - To Ladd from Dictionary of American Biography, from Gi-ichi Otaui in Kobe, Japan, 1932-1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Primarily to Ladd, regarding his illness, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Regarding socialism controversy at BDS
    - Primarily correspondence of others, regarding socialism controversy at Berkeley Divinity School, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - To/from Ladd and correspondence of others, 1920 January - February (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - To/from Ladd and correspondence of others, 1920 March - May (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - To/from Ladd and correspondence of others regarding socialism controversy - 3, 1920 June - 1921 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - To Ladd, no date (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Regarding Connecticut Child Welfare Commission
    - To/from Ladd, 1918 - 1919 August (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - To Ladd, 1919 September - 1920 January (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - To Ladd, 1920 February - May (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - To Ladd, 1920 June - December (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - To Ladd, 1921 January - May (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Regarding "Prayer Book Interleaves"
    - Correspondence and comments regarding publication by Ladd, 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence and comments, 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence and comments, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence and comments, 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Writings and Notes of Ladd, 1897-1940; Series II
  - Sermons and prayers
    - Dated, 1897-1898 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Dated, 1900-1914 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Dated, 1923-1929 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Dated, 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Dated, 1934-1939 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Dated, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Sermons and notes labeled "Christian Year", 1919-1930, no date (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Undated, no date (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Undated, no date (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Undated, no date (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Undated, no date (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Undated, no date (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Addresses and talks
    - Addresses at beginning of school year, Berkeley Divinity School, 1933, 1935-1937 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Including "What is the Church", "Teaching Children Morals and Manners", "Christian Ethics from the Historical Point of View", 1929-1939 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Including "Theodore of Tarsus, Greek, Roman, and Anglican", "The Relation of the Christian Community to the Experience of Salvation", "What is the Church?", no date (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Including "Motives for Foreign Missions", untitled, and notes, no date (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Essays and articles
    - Articles in The Churchman, including "Does the Modern World Need Theology?", 1919-1939 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Articles in The Living Church, including "Our Sunday School Failure", "Puritan vs. Anglican", 1906-1929 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Articles in The Witness, The Layman's Magazine, Divinity School Progress, 1919-1940 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Letter to Editor in The American Hebrew, tract "Why Bishops", 1925, no date (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - "Prayer Book Inter-Leaves" - columns published in The Witness, no date (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - "A Bird's Eye View of Church History" - series published in The Churchman, 1913-1914 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - "A Bird's Eye View of Church History" - notes and drafts, no date (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - "A Bird's Eye View of Church History" - notes and drafts, no date (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - "A Bird's Eye View of Church History" - notes and drafts, no date (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - "A Bird's Eye View of Church History" - notes and drafts, no date (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Illustrations for articles and related correspondence, 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Typescript and handwritten essays, including "Bolshevism at Berkeley", 1930, no date (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Notes and Source Materials
    - Book of notes and source materials, no date (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Handwritten notes and printed source materials, no date (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Course-related materials, 1929-1941 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Collected Material, 1910-1943; Series III
  - Writings of others
    - Including prayers, devotionals, issue of The Churchman, 1923-1939 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Prayers, typed documents, and articles, 1910-1943 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Socialism controversy material
    - Typescript documents, 1919 December (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Scope and Contents
      including "Minutes of hearing before a Special Committee appointed by Bishop Brewster to investigate the utterances of one Wilfred Humphreys at Berkeley Divinity School December 2, 1919" and "Notes on Mr. Humphries' Lecture on Russia"
    - Typescript documents, 1920 January - April (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Including "Hearing at Berkeley Divinity School, Middletown, Conn."
    - Typescript documents, no date (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Including "A Summary of a Report Prepared for the Trustees of the Berkeley Divinity School on the Charges Against the School and its Dean"
    - Pamphlets and articles, 1920-1921 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      Including "A Statement by Dean Ladd" reprinted from The Hartford Courant
    - Compilations of newspaper clippings - three volumes, 1919-1920 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Newspaper clippings (photocopies), 1919 December (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Newspaper clippings (photocopies), 1920 January (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Newspaper clippings (photocopies), 1920 February (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Newspaper clippings (photocopies), 1920 March (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper clippings (photocopies), 1920 June (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Newspaper clippings (photocopies), 1920 July (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Newspaper clippings (photocopies), 1920 November (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Newspaper clippings (photocopies), no date (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Child Welfare Commission material - by Ladd and others
    - Reports, minutes, and other notes, 1919-1920 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Articles and notes, 1921 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, Series IV
  - Photograph of Ladd, no date (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Article relating to family history of Ladd by Rosalind Ekman Ladd, in Historical New Hampshire, 2014 (Box 7, Folder 10)